Essex Company Glass Plate Negatives 6633 GPN
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Essex Company Glass Plate Negatives
1890-1927
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Essex Company (Lawrence, Mass.)
6633 GPN
27.25 cubic feet
27.2 linear ft.
glass plate negatives.
Photographs of water turbines, canal construction and repair, storm damage, as well as other subjects. Most of the photographs were taken in Lawrence, Massachusetts.
10060226
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, January 04, 2018
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, January 04, 2018
Biographical / Historical
The Essex Company was charted in 1845 to build a dam and canals on the Merrimack River to provide power for textile mills, with the intent to build a planned city, Lawrence, Massachusetts. The company also built several mills and mill machinery.
In the 1830s Daniel Saunders began buying land on either side of the Merrimack River between Lowell and Andover, in order control the water power rights. With his son, Daniel Saunders, Jr., his uncle, J. Abbot Gardiner, and John Nesmith, he established the Merrimack River Power Association. Saunders then approached the Lawrence brothers (Samuel, Amos, and Abbott) and the Boston Associates. The Boston Associates bought the Merrimack Water Power Association and renamed it the Essex Company.
When Lawrence was incorporated as a town in 1847 and a city in 1853, the Essex Company laid out the streets and built much of the infrastructure. The City Hall and churches were built on land donated by the Essex Company.
Unique among the mill towns in New England, Lawrence, Massachusetts, was planned and development controlled due to the fact that the Essex Company owned most of the land along both sides of the river. The company further controlled development by buying, jointly with Lowell's Proprietors of Locks and Canals, land and water rights along the Merrimack River up to Lake Winnipesaukee, in New Hampshire. This led to the Essex Company becoming a pioneer in water and sewage treatment, developing the United States' first slow sand filter for drinking water.
In 1979 a hydroelectric company acquired the Essex Company in order to make use of the dam.
The above organizational history was condensed from The Lawrence History Center's Administrative History for their Records of the Essex Company of Lawrence, Massachusetts, 1845-1987.
Scope and Contents
Photographs of water turbines, canal construction and repair, flooding from spring runoff (freshets), ice dams, various buildings in the Lawrence, Massachusetts, area. Also included are photographs of scenery, family groups, houses, and othe buildings. Hurricane and tornado damage are also pictured.
These negatives have been printed. The prints can be found in Collection 6633 P, boxes 1-10.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6633: Essex Company Records 6633 G: Essex Company Graphics 6633 P: Essex Company Photographs 6633 PUBS: Essex Company Publications Records of the Essex Company of Lawrence, Massachusetts, 1845-1987, Lawrence History Center Immigrant City Archives an Museum, Lawrence, Massachusetts
Business records; Hydraulic engineers -- Massachusetts.; Industrial relations; Penstocks; Reservoirs -- Massachusetts -- Lawrence.; Textile industry -- Power supply -- Massachusetts -- Lawrence.; Water rights; Water-power -- Massachusetts -- Lawrence.; Water-wheels; Andover Bridge (Andover, MA).; Lawrence (Mass.) -- History -- 19th century.; Lawrence (Mass.) -- History -- 20th century.; Merrimack River (N.H. and Mass.) -- Power untilization; Bartlett, Edward.; Bigelow, Charles H.; Hale, Richard A.; Lawrence, Samuel, 1801-1880.; Marvel, C. M.; Mills, Hiram F. (Hiram Francis), 1836-1921; Morse, John.; Nesmith, John.; Rollins, John R. (John Rodman), 1817-1892.; Saunders, Daniel, 1796-1872.; Storrow, Charles S. (Charles Storer), -- 1809-1904.; Tewksbury, Robert H. (Robert Haskell), 1833-; Essex Company (Lawrence, Mass.); Lawrence Machine Shop; Lawrence Reservoir Association.; Middlesex Company.; Winnepissiogee Lake Cotton and Woolen Manufacturing Company.
10060226
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 1)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 1, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 2)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 3)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1890 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 1, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 4)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1890 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 5)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1900 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 1, Folder 6
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 6)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1900 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 7)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 1, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 8)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1982-1900 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 9)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 1, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 10)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 11)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 1, Folder 7
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 12)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 13)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 2, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 14)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 15)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 2, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 16)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 17)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1982-1910 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 2, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 18)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1982-1910 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 19)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1910 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 2, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 20)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1910 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 21)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1910 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 2, Folder 5
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 22)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1910 (Box 22, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 23)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1895 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 3, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 24)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1895 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 25)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1914 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 3, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 26)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1914 (Box 26, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 27)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1911 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 3, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 28)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1911 (Box 28, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 29)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1896-1916 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 3, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 30)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1896-1916 (Box 30, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 31)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1897-1911 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 3, Folder 5
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 32)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1897-1911 (Box 32, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 33)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1911 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 4, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 34)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1911 (Box 34, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 35)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1897 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 4, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 36)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1897 (Box 36, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 37)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1908 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 4, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 38)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1908 (Box 38, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 39)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1913-1925 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 4, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 40)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1913-1925 (Box 40, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 41)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1910-1925 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 4, Folder 5
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 42)
  - 5 x 7 glass plates., 1910-1925 (Box 42, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 43)
  - Negatives 105 - 126. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1914 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 5, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 44)
  - Negatives 127 - 145. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1914 (Box 44, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 45)
  - Negatives 146 - 158. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1897 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 5, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 46)
  - Negatives 159 - 186. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1897 (Box 46, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 47)
  - Negatives 187 - 198. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1897 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 5, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 48)
  - Negatives 199 - 218. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893-1897 (Box 48, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 49)
  - Negatives 219 - 236. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1897-1915 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 5, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 50)
  - Negatives 237 - 262. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1897-1915 (Box 50, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 51)
  - Negatives 263 - 279. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1914 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 5, Folder 5
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 52)
  - Negatives 280 - 295. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1915 (Box 52, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 53)
  - Negatives 296 - 307. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 53, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 5, Folder 6
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 54)
  - Negatives 308 - 321. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 54, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 55)
  - Negatives 322 - 337. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893 (Box 55, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 6, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 56)
  - Negatives 338 - 357. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893 (Box 56, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 57)
  - Negatives 358 - 372. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 6, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 58)
  - Negatives 373 - 394. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 58, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 59)
  - Negatives 395 - 414. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 6, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 60)
  - Negatives 415 - 435. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1893 (Box 60, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 61)
  - Negatives 436 - 459-1. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 6, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 62)
  - Negatives 459-2 - 480. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1893 (Box 62, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 63)
  - Negatives 481 - 495. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1894 (Box 63, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 6, Folder 5
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 64)
  - Negatives 496 - 516. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1892-1894 (Box 64, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 65)
  - Negatives 517 - 535. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894 (Box 65, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 6, Folder 6
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 66)
  - Negatives 536 - 549. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 66, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 67)
  - Negatives 550 - 562-1. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1896 (Box 67, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 7, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 68)
  - Negatives 562-2 - 583. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1896 (Box 68, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 69)
  - Negatives 584 - 603. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895 (Box 69, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 7, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 70)
  - Negatives 604 - 620. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895 (Box 70, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 71)
  - Negatives 621 - 633. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1896 (Box 71, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 7, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 72)
  - Negatives 634 - 651. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1896 (Box 72, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 73)
  - Negatives 652 - 674. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1896 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 7, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 74)
  - Negatives 675 - 689. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1896 (Box 74, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 75)
  - Negatives 690 - 702. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1896 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 7, Folder 5
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 76)
  - Negatives 703 - 722. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1896 (Box 76, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 77)
  - Negatives 723 - 753. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1897 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 7, Folder 6
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 78)
  - Negatives 754 - 772. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1897 (Box 78, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 79)
  - Negatives 773 - 791. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1895 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 8, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 80)
  - Negatives 792 - 808. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1894-1895 (Box 80, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 81)
  - Negatives 809 - 825. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1898 (Box 81, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 8, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 82)
  - Negatives 827 - 845. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1895-1898 (Box 82, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 83)
  - Negatives 846 - 865. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1898-1899 (Box 83, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 8, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 84)
  - Negatives 866 - 880. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1898-1899 (Box 84, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 85)
  - Negatives 881 - 899. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1898-1899 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 8, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 86)
  - Negatives 900 - 920. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1898-1899 (Box 86, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 87)
  - Negatives 921 - 940. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1897-1898 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 8, Folder 5
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 88)
  - Negatives 941 - 960. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1897-1898 (Box 88, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 89)
  - Negatives 961 - 980. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1897-1899 (Box 89, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 9, Folder 1
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 90)
  - Negatives 981 - 999. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1897-1899 (Box 90, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 91)
  - Miscellaneous. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1899-1920 (Box 91, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 9, Folder 2
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 92)
  - Miscellaneous. 5 x 7 glass plates., 1921-1927 (Box 92, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 9, Folder 3
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 93)
  - Miscellaneous and Island Pond. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 93, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 94)
  - Miscellaneous and Island Pond. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 94, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 9, Folder 4
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 95)
  - Miscellaneous. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 95, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 96)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 96, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 9, Folder 5
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 97)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 97, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 98)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 98, Folder 1)
    For prints of these negatives see 6633 P Box 9, Folder 6
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 99)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 99, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 100)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 100, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 101)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 101, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 102)
  - Miscellaneous and Country Views. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 102, Folder 1)
- 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 103)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified. 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 103, Folder 1)
- 8x10 glass plate negatives (Box 104)
  - Miscellaneous and Pages from a Book on Velocities. 8 x 10 glass plates. (Box 104, Folder 1)
- 8x10 glass plate negatives (Box 105)
  - Miscellaneous and Pages from a Book on Velocities. 8 x 10 glass plates. (Box 105, Folder 1)
- 8x10 glass plate negatives (Box 106)
  - Miscellaneous and Sloop of War "Fairfield". 8 x 10 glass plates. (Box 106, Folder 1)
- 8x10 glass plate negatives (Box 107)
  - Miscellaneous. 8 x 10 glass plates. (Box 107, Folder 1)
- 8x10 and 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 108)
  - Miscellaneous, Some Broken. 8 x 10 and 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 108, Folder 1)
- 8x10 and 5x7 glass plate negatives (Box 109)
  - Miscellaneous, Some Broken. 8 x 10 and 5 x 7 glass plates. (Box 109, Folder 1)